1915年12月
显得再英勇些
Look brave.
谢谢你 上尉 安斯沃思太太
Thank you, Captain, Mrs Ainsworth.
真的不让我去车站送你吗
Can't I come to the station?
我并没有那么英勇
I'm not that brave.
噢 我亲爱的莉齐
Oh, my darling Lizzie.
深影字幕组
翻译 等位基因A LYP 大力 Bazinga jimbert
校对 君君不黑
压制 芒果
谋杀巧艺
SIMPLE ART OF MURDER
寓所谜案
THE MURDER AT THE VICARAGE
鸡蛋又是硬的 玛丽
My egg was hard again, Mary
怪生蛋的母鸡去吧
Blame the chicken.
不行
No.
噢 不行
Oh, no.
还行
Yes.
丹尼斯
Dennis
大周末的非要这样弄吗
Must you, on a Sunday?
抱歉 伦奥纳德叔叔 但她出毛病了
Sorry, Uncle Leonard, but she's playing up.
你这样子不能去教堂啊
You can't go to church like that.
噢 反正我也没想去 修这个要很久呢
Oh, I'm not anyway. This could be a long job.
- 玛丽! - 她不会听得见的
- Mary! - She won't hear you.
煮个蛋都煮不好
Can't even boil an egg!
我们也只请得起她这样的了 你这个老可怜
She's all we can afford, you old misery.
你娶我的时候就清楚我不会做饭
You knew I couldn't cook when you married me.
而你也清楚我老了
And you knew I was old.
看下时间!
Look at the time!
噢
Oh.
- 早上好 马普尔小姐 - 早上好
- Morning, Miss Marple. - Good morning.
你是怎么做到的 格丽泽尔达
How did you manage that, Griselda?
他终于能早到一次了
He'll be early for once.
阿加莎・克里斯蒂: 马普尔小姐探案集
第一季第二集
我晚上再告诉你吧 简
I shall tell you this evening, Jane.
记得带你的西洋李子金酒过来
And bring some your damson gin over
或许能弥补一下玛丽糟糕的厨艺
It might take the edge off Mary's cooking.
# 夏日再次到来 #
The summer days are come again
# 大地再次欢快雀跃 #
Once more the glad earth yields
# 夏日乔木深深的影子 #
And deepening shade of summer woods
# 热辣的空气闪闪发光 #
And glow of summer air
# 那些飞舞的思绪和喜悦的心情 #
And winging thoughts and happy moods
# 关于爱与欢乐与祈祷 #
Of love and joy and prayer...
但各人被试探
But every man is tempted
乃是被自己的私欲牵引诱惑的
when he is drawn away of his own lust, and enticed.
私欲既怀了胎
Then when lust hath conceived,
就生出罪来
it bringeth forth sin,
罪既长成
and sin, when it is finished,
就生出死来
bringeth forth death.
今天的选读到此结束
Here endeth the lesson.
别扭来扭去了 莱蒂斯!
Stop wriggling, Lettice!
- 是莱提丝 - 大家都叫你莱蒂斯
- It's Letteece - Everyone calls you Lettice.
你和大家不一样 劳伦斯
You're not everyone, Lawrence.
规矩点 别忘了你在哪里
Behave. Don't forget where you are.
别动
Steady.
你应该画成一本日历
You should be on a calendar.
然后挂在你父亲的书房里
We could hang it in your father's study.
噢 劳伦斯
Oh, Lawrence.
鬼鬼祟祟的 大饱眼福了?
Get an eyeful, creeping around?
她穿着泳衣呢
She's in her bathing suit.
列丁先生是个艺术家
Mr Redding's an artist.
对他来说 这就像是在看一碗樱桃
It's like looking at a bowl of cherries for him.
除非她把泳衣脱掉
Until she takes it off.
你的鼻子沾了汽油呢
You've got an oily nose.
上周日的英国国教
Last Sunday's collection
传道会的捐款中筹得了
in aid of the Church of England Missionary Society,
总共十八先令和十一便士 做得很好 各位
a total of 18 shillings and 11 pences. Well done, everybody.
- 这肯定搞错了 - 什么?
- That can't be right. - What?
传道会将大大受益于我们做出的努力
The society benefits enormously from the efforts we make.
我一个人就捐了一磅
I put in a pound to myself.
我这里有一封来自传道会的感谢信
I have here a letter of thanks from the secretary.
上校
Colonel...
怎么了 玛乔丽?
Yes, Marjorie?
- 这不对劲 - 什么?
- There's something wrong... - What?
嘘!
Shh!
- 什么? - 嘘
- What? - Shh.
你真的确定吗
You are quite sure?
在可怜的布鲁斯的忌日那天
I always put a pound note into the box
我总会投张一英镑的钞票进筹款箱
on the anniversary of poor Bruce's passing.
我知道 但也许这次
I know, but perhaps this time...
得了吧 马普尔小姐
Come on, Miss Marple!
如果玛乔丽说她放了一英镑
If Marjorie says she put a pound in
那她肯定放了 那这钱哪去了呢
then she did, so where's it gone?
我还以为你会紧抓住
I thought you'd be straining
这引领找出罪恶的绳子呢
at the leash to sniff out the culprit.
你在发现罪恶方面的确小有名气啊
You do have a reputation to maintain.
普罗瑟罗上校 您太过奖了
My reputation, Colonel Protheroe, if I have one
如果我真的有点名气的话 那也与此无关
how very kind of you to suggest I do - is neither here nor there.
我只是想现在谈及罪恶是否言之过早了
I merely wonder if it's too early to talk of culprits.
- 荒谬 - 卢修斯
- Nonsense! - Lucius.
安妮 别挠我
Anne, don't paw me.
好了 听着 我是教区委员 且我并不傻
Now, look. I'm a church warden, and I was in intelligence.
我看得出这里面有猫腻
I know when something smells fishy.
这可能还只是冰山一角 牧师!
It could be the tip of the iceberg. Vicar!
简 我们明天换个地方吧 试试三角帽酒馆
Jane, shall we try the Toby Jug tomorrow just for a change?
好主意
Good idea.
莱蒂斯今天早上去哪里了
Where's Lettice this morning?
- 列丁先生在为她画肖像 - 在周日画?
- Mr Redding's painting her. - On a Sunday?
- 嗯 - 你不觉得...
- Mm-hm. - You don't think...?
他的确很有一套 但她还是个小女孩
He does have a way with him, but she's just a girl.
如果真有情人的话 我想他会选年纪大点的
I'd plump for an older candidate if there is somebody.
别忘了明天下午四点半的八卦茶话会哦
Don't forget, ladies, tea and scandal tomorrow at 4:30.
还有 我已经邀请了莱斯特太太 我来啦
And I've invited Mrs Lester. I'm coming!
或许我们能了解她多一点
Perhaps we'll find out a little more about her.
首先要了解的是为什么她喜欢住在蓝野猪旅馆
Something would be a start. Fancy staying at the Blue Boar.
那里和她不怎么相称
Not very homely for her.
收集很多东西 你懂我的意思吧
Very well-stocked, if you take my meaning.
- 噢? - 在义卖中积极出手
- Oh? - Tipsy at the jumble sale.
为什么我们亲爱的牧师非要选这么肤浅的妻子
Why the dear vicar had to choose such a shallow wife
而且以他这样的年纪
and at his age too...
我要求查看教区的全套账目
I expect to see a full set of parish accounts
否则我将进一步闹大此事
or I'm going to take this matter further.
- 好吧? - 你听明白我的意思了么?
- Yes? - Is that quite clear?
- 是的 - 那就周二六点十五分在你家见
- Yes. - Tuesday. Vicarage, 6:15 sharp.
我完全明白你的意思
I know just what you mean.
上校 您的房子建筑研究进展如何
Colonel, any news of your architectural sleuths?
噢 海多克医生
Yes, Dr Haydock.
他们昨晚抵达了
They arrived last night.
他们要拍照绘图 还有些乱七八糟的事
They'll be taking photographs and making drawings and "who-knows-what" .
但这就是拥有
Still One of the perils
像老屋这种重要建筑所要面对的
of owning an important house like Old Hall.
日安 医生
Good day, Doctor.
真是个讨厌的人
What a dreadful, dreadful man.
- 我走路吧 爸爸 - 不 上车
- I'll walk, Daddy. - No. Get in.
肖像画得怎么样了
How's the portrait coming along?
非常好 谢谢关心 安妮
Perfectly well, thank you, Anne.
莱蒂斯我还以为他画的是你穿着
Lettice...I thought he was painting you
- 漂亮蓝裙子的样子呢 - 是啊
- in that pretty blue dress of yours. - Yes...
但今天他只画我的手
but today he was just doing my hands
所以我就懒得穿了
so I didn't bother to wear it.
你那里放什么东西呢
What have you got in there?
没放什么
Nothing.
让我看看
Let me see.
给我
Come.
这 这更有艺术感
I-It's more artistic.
是艺术感还是情色
There's art and there's smut!
他居然敢?你居然敢!
How dare he? And how dare you?
嘘 嘘
Ssh, ssh.
看上帝的份上 别大声叫嚷
Don't shout, for godness' sake.
我自己的事自己处理 谢谢了 安妮
I'll fight my own battles. Thank you, Anne.
我只是在为我们的客人着想
I was thinking of our guests.
早上好 教授
Good morning, Professor.
需要的东西都齐全了吗
Do you have everything you need?
谢谢你 是的 你可爱的女儿帮了很多忙
Thank you, yes. Your so charming daughter was most helpful.
继女儿
Stepdaughter.
啊 睡美人醒来了
对不起 爷爷 早上好
Je m'excuse, grand-pare. Good morning.
早上好 小姐 午餐是在十二点半
Morning, mademoiselle. Lunch will be served at half past twelve.
我丈夫很希望能听到你们的研究成果
My husband's very keen to hear about your research.
我们很荣幸 对吧 爷爷
We are flattered, aren't we, Grandfather?
不及我丈夫那么荣幸
Not as much as he is.
居然允许在你的花园里出现这样的行为 牧师
Permitting that sort of behaviour in your own garden, Vicar?
不 不 我是说这 这完全不能被接受
No, no. I mean it's... it's utterly unacceptable.
好了 请把列丁先生的电话号码给我
Now, Mr Redding's telephone number, please.
这里真美啊
Isn't it gorgeous?
没有什么能像英国的夏日傍晚那样迷人
Nothing quite so beautiful as an English summer's evening.
送给我们的女主人的吗 真悦目
For our hostess? How lovely!
我听说你手里的酒更让人愉悦
Not as lovely as that stuff, I hear.
走吧?
Shall we?
噢 谢谢你
Oh, thank you.
感谢主赐给我们这食物 祝福我们能热爱
Bless this food to our use and us to thy loving
忠诚地服事您
and faithful service
这是由您的大地养分以及人类劳动
nourished by the fruit of your earth
所带来的收获
and by the work of human hands.
让我们以真诚的顺从回报您 主
May we render you true obedience, Lord
并服从您的意愿
and bend ourselves to thy will.
并让我们永远谨记为自己服务
And make us ever needful of the minds of others.
呃 为他人服务 阿门
Er, ever mindful of the needs of others. Amen.
阿门
Amen.
好吧 我只能道歉
Well, I can only apologise.
噢 反正上校总是找借口批评这批评那的
The colonel's always looking for an excuse to criticise.
我想你画中的格丽泽尔达不是穿着泳衣吧
I hope you're not painting Griselda in a bathing suit?
马普尔小姐 那太恶心了
Miss Marple, that's disgusting.
- 谢谢你 - 当然不是
- Thank you. - Certainly not.
但你一定要来看看 克莱蒙特先生
But you must come to see it, Mr Clement.
画正好到了一个很有趣的阶段
It's at that very interesting stage.
- 像丹尼斯那样吗 - 噢 真好笑
- Like Dennis? - Oh, ha-ha.
- 明天下午茶时间来一下吧 - 好的
- Pop over tomorrow, around teatime. - I will.
- 这是什么 玛丽 - 汤
- What is this, Mary? - Soup.
它有名字吗
Does it have a name?
"稀里糊涂乱切一气
"bis and bobs and odds and sods
再加上点肉丁"汤
and the meat raion's been cut again" soup.
抱歉 抱歉
Sorry. Sorry.
你今晚精神很紧张不安啊 豪伊斯先生
You're a bag of nerves this evening, Mr Hawes.
不仅是今晚 请给我一杯水好吗
Not just tonight. May I have a glass of water?
- 还有人要水吗 - 不了 谢谢你
- Anyone else? - No, thank you.
要知道 这都是我的药在起作用
If it wasn't for my medicine, you see...
别担心 神经质又不会传染
Don't worry, you can't catch nerves.
这是慈悲的主赐给我的不幸的折磨修行
It's a wretched affliction I bear with God's grace.
说到不幸的折磨
Talking of wretched afflictions
罗尼 普罗瑟罗上校要周二见我
Ronnie, Colonel Protheroe on Tuesday.
你能整理一下教区账目吗
Can you get the parish accounts into some sort of order?
- 我尽力 - 有时我真想勒死普罗瑟罗
- I'll try. - I could strangle Protheroe sometimes.
- 愿主宽恕我 - 我会扎死他
- May God forgive me. - I'd stab him.
- 我会毒死他 - 我会一枪打死他
- I'd poison him. - I'd shoot him.
- 用我的枪 - 他对莱蒂斯真是太坏了
- Use my gun. - He's so rotten to Lettice.
- 噢 - 就因为他买下了老屋
- Aw. - Just because he bought Old Hall,
他就以为自己是个乡绅地主什么的
he thinks he's the local squire something.
你不能那样对别人啊
You can't treat people like that now.
你说得没错 那你会怎么做呢 马普尔小姐
You're quite right. And how would you do it, Miss Marple?
我从不随便谈论谋杀 列丁先生
I never speak lightly of murder, Mr Redding.
我讨厌冒不必要的险
I hate to tempt fate.
当然在这美丽地方是不会发生的啊
Surely not in this lovely place?
我们都只是圣玛丽・米德村的平凡人
We're all very ordinary in St Mary Mead,
但平凡人有时候会做出最惊人的事
but ordinary people sometimes do the most astonishing things
- 你是真的有手枪吗 - 是啊 是德国枪
- Do you really have a pistol? - Somewhere. It's German.
- 我偷出来的 - 你还真是勇敢啊
- I liberated it. - Were you wonderfully brave?
虽受过良好训练 但还是很怕死
Very well-trained, but scared to death.
五分钟后 我就清桌上菜
I'll clear in five minutes.
炖萝卜和鱼 主要是萝卜
Fish and turnip stew-mostly turnip.
噢 麻烦拿一下杏子酸辣酱
Oh, bring the apricot chutney, will you?
圣玛丽・米德村牧师寓所
St Mary Mead vicarage.
不 弗兰克 我不可以
No, Frankie, I can't.
但你母亲会在那里的
But you'lI have your mum there.
法官是谁
Who's the magistrate?
那就起码要两磅罚款了
That'll be two-quid fine at least
我们怎么能存到这么多的...
How are we ever going to save up to get a...
我很抱歉 但你打错号码了
I am very sorry but you have mistook a wrong number.
我禁止你再去见他
I forbid you to see him again!
他只是在为我画肖像
He was only painting me.
我倒是希望他做了什么蠢事
I wish he were doing something else stupid
看你大惊小怪的
the fuss you're making.
- 别没大没小! - 那你也别讨人厌啊
- Don't be common! - Well, don't be horrid, then.
就因为你的坏脾气 杜福斯爷孙都借辞回床了
You've driven the Dufosses to bed because your foul mood.
- 好啊 你也可以滚回去啊 - 非常乐意
- Well, you blood can go too! - Gladly.
坐下 我们还没吃完呢
Sit down. We haven't finished.
晚安 卢修斯
Good night, Lucius.
有一些人会觉得
There are those
偷猎是一种英雄传奇式的行为 塔兰特
who take a romantic view of poaching, Tarrant.
但我不这么觉得
I do not.
这次 你要坐牢了
This time, you'll go to prison.
先生 你不能这样 先生
Sir, you can't, sir!
- 没事的 妈妈 - 夫人 坐下
- All right, Mum. - Madam, sit down.
监禁二十八天
28 days.
我会丢掉工作的 你这老混蛋
I'll lose my job, you old bastard.
二十九天
29.
圣玛丽・米德村牧师寓所
St Mary Mead vicarage.
这并不公正!
It's not fair!
- 玛丽? - 我要出去
- Mary? - I'm going out!
问题不仅是年龄上的差距 简
It's not just the difference in our ages, Jane.
牧师和他的妻子也能很开心啊
The vicar and his wife are perfectly happy.
我想他们有了孩子会更开心
They'd be happier with a child, I think.
那也是他们共同的孩子
It would be their own.
莱蒂斯母亲去世时 她才两岁
Lettice was two when her mother died.
到我嫁给卢修斯的时候 她已经长大了
By the time I married Lucius, she was too old to think of me
只会觉得我是个可恶的继母
as anything other than the wicked stepmother.
我总惹她烦 而且
I get on her nerves, and...
恐怕 她也老惹得我烦
..I'm afraid she gets on mine.
这一切让他生气 甚至比平时更生气
That makes him angry - even angrier than normal.
你们有没有想过要个共同的孩子
Might you have a child of your own one day?
没有
No.
那 那方面的事情已经
That...side of things has...
很少进行了
dwindled rather.
其实是完全没有了
Completely.
我需要温柔的对待 简
I need tenderness, Jane.
而那与他本性相违
And that's just not in his nature.
谢谢你
Thank you.
对不起
Sorry.
噢 我们不时都会有些话不吐不快
Oh, we all have to get things off our chest occasionally.
但是 我嫁给他是为了安定下来
Still... I married him for a kind of certainty.
战争之后 我们都想要安定下来 不是吗
We all wanted certainty after the war, didn't we?
我应该满足于我所得到的
I must settle for what I've got.
- 凑凑活活过下去? - 凑活吧
- Make do and mend? - Make do.
而且至少 我曾被温柔地对待过
And at least there once was someone tender,
但他没有从战场上回来
but he didn't come back from the fighting.
简 我就知道你会来
Jane, I knew you'd come.
- 我必须来 - 噢 亲爱的
- I had to. - Oh, my darling.
我们的车来了
There's our lift
我们最好别让他等久了
We'd better not keep him waiting.
该死的蠢蛋!
Bloody fool!
扶我一把!
Help me!
你受伤了吗
Are you hurt?
没有 噢!
No. Oh!
- 伤了 - 伤到脚踝了
- Yes. - Caught her ankle.
噢...
Oh...
我实在是太抱歉了
I'm so terribly sorry.
这不是你的错
It wasn't your fault.
一定要这样来固定关节
It has to support the sprain.
我车里还有一根拐杖
I have a stick in the car.
明天你就可以拄着拐杖走动了
You might be able to hobble by tomorrow.
我可不想拄着拐杖 海多克医生
I don't want to be a hobbler, Dr Haydock.
要我煮些茶么?
Shall I make some tea?
显然不必了
Apparently, that won't be necessary.
看来八卦茶话会正朝着我们过来了
It seems tea and scandal are coming to us.
我迷路了 有着弗兰芒挂毯和天花板很高
I am lost. The small drawing room with the Flemish tapestry
的小画室在哪里
and the magnificent ceiling?
另一边再过去两间 这是我父亲的书房
Two down on the other side. That's my father's study.
听到我来了吧
Heard me, then?
怎么可能听不到啊 丹尼斯
How could I not, Dennis?
- 要不要去兜风? - 坐那玩意去?
- Want to go for a ride? - On that thing?
去年我们不就
Last year, we...
去年我只有十六岁 所以才觉得好玩
Last year I was 16 and it was fun.
好吧 我也没见劳伦斯・列丁开着跑车啊
Well, I haven't seen Lawrence Redding in a sports car.
如果他有钱就会开了
He would if he had the money
而且他看起来超级...成熟
and he'd look so wonderfully...mature.
明天一起打网球?
See you tomorrow for tennis?
噢 没错 和丹尼斯打网球
Oh, yes, tennis with Dennis.
他怎样了
How did he get on?
一个月监禁 普罗瑟罗判的
A month inside. Protheroe.
列丁先生 你该把这个锁起来
Mr Redding, you should shut this away.
或许吧
Probably.
这是给你的 下次在蓝野猪旅馆再见了
Here's one for you next time you're in the Blue Boar.
你确定不需要我走的时候把门锁好?
You sure you don't want me to start locking up when I go?
这可是英国人的特色啊 塔太太
This is the heart of England, Mrs T.
再说 锁住房门就是把爱拒绝在外
Besides, lock up the house and you lock out love.
噢 我的天 穿着泳衣吗
Oh, my Lord! In her bathing suit?
在我看来 上校肯定会很不高兴
The colonel won't have liked that from what I've seen.
他脾气火爆得像屁股着了火一样
Looks like he's got a poker up his bum.
火还不小呢
At least one.
你准备呆在圣玛丽・米德村吗 莱斯特太太
Will you be staying long in St Mary Mead, Mrs Lester?
叫我西尔维娅就好了
Sylvia, please.
我想再住会看看
I shall have to see.
对你来说 我们不会太静了吗
We're not too quiet for you?
的确风平浪静 但改变和宁静也是好事
Like a millpond. But a change is as good as a rest.
具体是什么样的转变呢
A change...from what...exactly?
从我匆忙的生活中转变过来啊 哈特内尔小姐
My helter-skelter life, Miss Hartnell.
请恕我失陪了 我要去
If you'll excuse me, I must...
我要去看看格丽泽尔达的肖像画画得怎么样了
I must see how Griselda's portrait is coming along.
我真心希望你会喜欢 亲爱的
I do hope you like it, darling.
- 再见 - 再见
- Goodbye. - Bye.
- 下午好 牧师 - 再见
- Good afternoon, Vicar. - Goodbye.
那列丁画你的时候 你穿的是什么
And what are you wearing for Mr. Redding?
只是我的尊严 普赖斯・里德利太太
Just my dignity, Mrs. Price-Ridley,
还有一条粉红长围巾
and a pink feather boa.
是吗 格丽泽尔达
Really, Griselda!
我想我该去加点茶了
I think I'll just refresh the pot.
好了 谁想在大吉岭茶里面加点料
Now, who'd like a stiffener in their Darjeeling?
噢 我
Oh, I...
- 牧师 - 不
- Vicar... - No...
我忘了你要过来
I'd forgotten you were coming.
他该不是也在画普罗瑟罗太太的泳衣画吧
Is he doing Mrs. Protheroe too?
他的画笔可真是忙啊
Quite a busy boy with his brush.
她想要一起去伦敦 但是
She offered to come to London, but...
哎 我来这里就是为了逃避那里的
Well, I came here to get away from it and...
嗯 安妮不会适应的
Well, Anne wouldn't be suited to the...
我在那里的疯狂生活
the madness of my life there.
而我也不想她去适应 我对此疲倦了
And I wouldn't want her to be. I'm tired of it.
我厌倦了疯狂的生活
I'm tired of being wild.
对我们来说 你们现在就够疯狂了
You're quite wild enough for us.
我只觉得让你们失望了
I just feel that I've let you all down.
我在圣玛丽・米德村的日子
I've been happier in St Mary Mead
是我最开心的生活时光
than I've ever been in my life.
我觉得连我的作品都变好了
Even my work's better, I think.
无疑是少了些轻狂
That's certainly less wild.
但你必须做个了断
But you must end it.
- 我做不到 - 那你应该考虑离开这里
- I can't. - Then you should consider leaving.
为她的声誉着想吧
Think of her reputation.
你是唯一知道的人
You are the only one who knows.
暂时而已 在这里只要打个喷嚏大家就能
Yet. You only have to sneeze in this village for someone to...
伯恩小姐带下周的花来了
Miss Bourne's here about next week's flowers.
噢 她迟到了 这可不像她
Oh, she's late. That's not like her.
请一定要仔细考虑我刚才说的话
Please, please think about what I've said.
晚上好 这里是老屋
Old Hall. Good evening.
是的 他在 请问你的名字是?
Yes, he is. Who shall I say?
我需要禀告您的名字 夫人
I'll have to give a name, madam.
仅限住客进入
RESIDENTS ONLY
你想怎么样 西尔维娅?
What do you want, Sylvia?
告诉你些事情
To tell you something,
再看看你那冷峻的嘴唇
and see that stiff upper lip wobble
像面对着行刑队那样地颤抖
as if you were facing a firing squad.
吸着人生最后一根烟
Last cigarette?
双眼被眼罩遮住
Blindfold?
行刑
Bang.
- 我明天就能上下楼梯了 - 要晨衣吗
- I'll manage the stairs by tomorrow. - Dressing gown?
要的 谢谢
Yes, please.
那幅肖像画怎么样
How was the portrait?
只匆匆看了一眼吧
A brief viewing?
- 你看到了 - 恐怕我们都看到了
- You saw. - I'm afraid we all did.
我告诉格丽泽尔达时 她都吓到了
Griselda was horrified when I told her.
如果普罗瑟罗发现的话
If Protheroe finds out...
我知道他是个混蛋 但毕竟安妮嫁给了他
Now, I know he's a brute, but Anne married him,
而我信仰婚姻的神圣
and I believe in the sanctity of marriage.
我多么幸运
I'm so lucky.
她本可以选择任何男人
She could have had anyone.
但她选择了你
She chose you.
这是我人生中最美好的三年时光
It's been the best three years of my life.
都收拾好了
Here we are.
梳子 镜子和书
Hairbrush, mirror and book.
这本书精彩吗
Is it a good read?
当然比生活精彩了 牧师
Betcha life it is, padre.
还需要从梳妆台上拿什么东西吗
Anything else from the dressing table?
不用了
No.
真美啊
Beautiful.
这一建筑时代的完美典范
A perfect example for this period.
的确 你们打算什么时候出版
Indeed. When are you going to publish?
我们杂志在秋天出刊
Autumn is the next edition of our journal.
这期介绍的全部都是英国乡下的建筑
It will be all English country houses.
我会从巴黎给你寄一本的 我会把这记下来
I will send you a copy from Paris. I'll make a note of it.
法国现况如何
How is France now?
法国啊 嗯 怎么说呢
France? And, well, what do you say?
我们在逐渐恢复繁荣
We are getting on our feet.
你们的战争怎么样
How was your war?
情况不妙啊
Bad things happened.
那你呢 上校
And yours, Colonel?
很遗憾 我...
Unfortunately, I, er...
我不被允许去讨论我的服役工作
I am not at liberty to discuss my service.
- 卢修斯 - 嗯 啊 你们日安
- Lucius - Hmm? Ah. Good day to you.
我五点半会回来
I'll be back on the 5:30.
审判之后我要与罗斯・哈金斯太太会面
I have a meeting with Mrs. Ross-Harkins after court.
别忘了六点十五分要到牧师寓所去
Don't forget the vicarage at a quarter past six.
梅尔切斯特没东西卖吗
Aren't there any sales in Melchester?
伦敦是伦敦
London is London.
好吧 别买太多东西了
Well, don't buy too much.
不会买很多的
There won't be too much!
- 丹尼斯要载我去 - 什么
- Dennis is taking me. - What?
- 只载到车站啦 - 哦
- Only to the station. - Oh.
- 再见 - 再见
- Bye. - Bye.
噢 你看看这刮痕
Oh, look at this scratch!
啊 那我的轮子呢
Well, what about my wheel?
是你自己没有留神 傻子!
You weren't looking, you fool!
我敢说 你肯定是想别的事 比如说那些账目
Mind on other things, I dare say, like those accounts.
你这是什么意思
What do you mean?
哼 以后你就知道了
Well, we'll see what I mean.
务必要在六点十五分之前把账目交给牧师
Just make sure the vicar has them for six fifteen.
要知道 这车是有刹车的
It does have brakes, you know, this car
天啊 女人!
Good God, woman!
谢谢你
Thank you.
- 啊 克莱蒙特太太 - 上校
- Ah, Mrs. Clement. - Colonel.
去梅尔切斯特吗
Melchester?
去伦敦
London.
我相信你们的花园小屋
I trust your garden shed
很快就会恢复到正当的用途上的
will shortly be restored to its proper purpose.
它从来就没有过不正当的用途
It has never had an improper purpose.
显然 我们的标准不一致
Clearly our standards are different.
的确很显然 我很高兴这么说
Clearly, I'm glad to say.
你说什么
I beg your pardon?
为什么你这么糟糕地对待伦
Why are you so dreadful to Len?
他是个正直的好人
He's a good, honest man
他努力想要在基督教慈善中以身作则
who tries to set an example of Christian charity.
或许这慈善做得太过到家了
Perhaps charity can begin too close to home.
去梅尔切斯特的票 谢谢
Return to Melchester, please.
列丁先生追在牧师后面
Mr. Redding ran after the vicar
普罗瑟罗太太的鞋都脱掉了
and Mrs. Protheroe had her shoes off
而且我敢说她连衬裙都露出来了
and I'm sure you could see her petticoat.
今早我去付账单的时候
When I went to pay my paper bill this morning,
弗洛莉・兰迪说她完全不惊讶
Florrie Ranby said she wasn't at all surprised,
当然了 马普尔小姐早猜到是年纪大点的情人
and, of course, Miss Marple knew it was someone older.
周日那天 上校的圣经选读真是贴切
The colonel read a most apt lesson on Sunday
如果他知道的话
had he but known it:
"私欲既怀了胎
"When lust hath conceived,
就生出罪来"
it bringeth forth sin."
我要去修理下这个了
I have to put this right.
我父母想要我去肯尼亚
My parents want me to go to Kenya
帮他们管理农场
help them manage the farm.
你明年可以试着申请大学
You could try for university next year.
如果有其他值得留下的理由 我会的
I would if I had something else to stay for.
丹尼斯 别的不说
Dennis... Apart from anything...
你也知道我爸爸那人
well, you know Daddy,
- 金钱或地位 - 而我两者皆无
- money or prospects. - Nought out of two.
- 你说 如果没有他的话 - 不
- You mean, if it wasn't for him...? - No.
谁知道呢?
Well, who knows?
我们不能单纯做朋友吗
Can't we just be friends?
你可以忘了劳伦斯
You can forget about Lawrence.
伦叔叔进屋撞见他和你继母在一起
Uncle Len walked in on him and your stepmother
而他并不是在画她
and he wasn't painting her.
- 让我来倒吧 - 谢谢你
- Shall I be mother? - Thank you.
要知道 我是真的爱她 而不仅是因为
I do love her, you know. It's not just about...
性?
Sex?
我一直在想牧师所说的人们终究会知道
I keep thinking about what the vicar said about people knowing,
而我也发现报刊商威尔太太
and I got a very strange look
看我的眼神怪怪的
in the newsagent's from Mrs. Whale.
嗯 她消息确实灵通
Well, she's got wind of things.
戈德沃斯先生就是因为听威尔太太提起
The only reason Mr. Goldworthy knew about his wife and the Gl
尼龙长袜和口香糖才知道
was when he heard Mrs. Whale mention the nylon stockings
他妻子和美国兵的出轨
and the chewing gum.
为了安妮 我必须得离开了
I'll have to leave, for Anne's sake.
那倒是很勇敢
That's very brave.
嗯 是的 我很快就会走出来的
Yes, well, I'll soon be over it.
你不会的
You won't.
很长一段时间里都不会
Not for a long while.
什么都瞒不过你 对吧 马普尔小姐
Nothing gets past you, Miss. Marple, does it?
几乎没有过 年轻人
Hardly ever, young man.
我现在就去跟牧师说
I'll tell the vicar now.
- 他没那么快回来吧 - 说的也是
- He won't be back from his calls yet. - Nor will he.
有一件事我是可以帮忙的 马普尔小姐
There is something I could do for you, Miss. Marple.
如果你愿意的话
If you'd like.
列丁先生在书房等你
Mr. Redding in the study.
这是正确的决定
It's the right decision.
你跟她说了吗
Have you told her?
- 我还没想到怎么说 - 会想到的
- I need to find the words. - You will.
你真信任我
Well, you're very trusting.
我自己都没有信心呢
I'm not that sure of myself.
我会把小屋打扫干净的
I'll clear out the shed.
谢谢你让我在那里暂住
Thank you for letting me set up in there.
这都是格丽泽尔达的主意
That was Griselda.
我还没完成她的肖像画呢
I never did finish her painting.
你是个很幸运的人
You're a very lucky man.
替我照顾她 好吗
Look after her for me, won't you?
我是说安妮
Anne, I mean.
现在 现在该怎么办
耐心点 让我想想
啊 玛丽 呃 低地农场的老艾博特先生
Ah, Mary. Erm, old Mr. Abbott over at Lower Farm,
他邻居来电说他又病重垂危了
his neighbour's telephoned to say he's poorly again,
所以我六点十五分之前都回不来了
so I won't be back by 6:15.
向普罗瑟罗上校道歉并请他等一下我
Apologise to Colonel Protheroe and ask him to wait for me.
我会尽量对他态度好点的
I'll be as nice as I can.
我现在还能记得
I can still see it now,
他来村里的第一天
his first day in the village.
在那一瞬间
It was one of those moments
我就知道一切都将会改变
when you know that nothing will ever be the same again.
他唤醒了我过去的回忆
He reminded me of what might have been...
那段对生活还有快乐希望的过去
...in the days when I still hoped for happiness.
要知道 去接受你改变不了的事情
There can be happiness in acceptance,
也会让你快乐起来
you know, of what can't change.
会吗
Can there?
谢谢你 简
Thank you, Jane.
谢什么呢
What for?
谢谢你没有批判我
For not judging me.
- 他晚点才会回来 - 噢 没关系
- He'll be late. - Oh, it's all right.
- 我可以等 - 不等也不行 对吧
- I'll wait. - You'll have to, won't you?
噢 谢谢你
Oh, thank you.
有一只可爱的小羽冠巧妇鸟
There's a sweet little crested
喜欢在这边小树林活动
wren that likes this side of the woods.
劳伦斯有提过以后的计划吗
Did Lawrence mention the future at all?
我去听吧
I'll go, I'll go.
圣玛丽・米德235号
St. Mary Mead 235.
那是找我的
It was for me.
- 找你的? - 说 是让我去牧师寓所
- For you? - I'm...wanted at the vicarage.
失陪了
Sorry.
晚上好 教授先生
Bonsoir, Monsieur le Professeur.
晚上好 夫人
Ah, bonsoir, madame.
真是适合散步的傍晚 对吧
A beautiful evening for walking, no?
要是我能走动的话就好了
If only I could.
噢
Oh.
再见 列丁先生
Goodbye, Mr. Redding.
晚上好 夫人
Bonsoir, madame.
你去哪里了
噢 随便走走而已
如果你们现在回去的话 我可以一起吗
If you're going back now, may I join you?
- 好啊 - 谢谢你
- Yes. - Thank you.
要大杯的 我今天过得糟透了
A large one. I've had a hell of a day.
晚上好 玛丽
Good evening, Mary.
- 跟上校一起在书房等吧 - 他也在吗
- Wait in the study with the colonel. - He's here?
是的
He is.
耶和华 求你将你的道指示我
Show me your ways, O Lord,
将你的路教训我
teach me your paths.
求你以你的真理引导我 教训我
Guide me in your truth and teach me.
耶和华 求你将你的道指示我
Show me your ways, O Lord,
将你的路教训我
teach me your paths.
求你以你的真理引导我 教训我 我要怎么做
Guide me in your truth and teach me. What must I do?
我要怎么做
What must I do?
你又过来找我吗
Did you want to see me again?
列丁先生?
Mr. Redding?
艾博特先生怎么样了?
How's Mr. Abbott?
在伯恩茅斯疗养呢
Convalescing in Bournemouth.
某些人的恶作剧
Someone's idea of a joke.
不 不 不
No, no. No.
我是斯莱克警督
Detective Inspector Slack.
我是伦奥纳德・克莱蒙特 这里的牧师
Leonard Clement. I'm the vicar.
从领子就看出来了 医生到了吗
The collar's a clue. Is the doctor here?
到了
Yes.
伦 发生什么事了
Len, what's going on?
粗略估计 刚死了半个小时
HaIf an hour, at a guess.
我开始检查的时候肯定不超过三十分钟
Certainly no more than 30 minutes before my examination.
那就是什么时候
Which was when?
呃 牧师刚好在六点三刻发现他的
Well, the vicar found him at just gone quarter to seven.
我就在这附近 当我6点50分到好了
I'm only down the road... Say I got here at ten to.
时间掐得真准
Almost spot on.
死亡时间大概是6点20分
Time of death about 6:20, then.
不用大概了
Better than almost.
给他点奖励吧
Give the man a coconut.
"亲爱的牧师
"Dear Vicar,
恐怕我不能再等了
I'm afraid I cannot wait for you any longer,
但我必须"
but must..."
- 就写到这里 - 被枪杀的?
- That's it. - Pistol?
是的
Yes.
这扇门总是开着的吗
Are these always open?
通常在这样的天气都开着
Usually, in this weather.
这么说 牧师接到假电话被叫出去
So, the vicar's called away with a bogus message,
凶手通过花园进来
murderer comes in through the garden.
死者当时背对着凶手在写便条
Victim writing a note with back turned.
这就是作案的手法和时间
That's how and when.
剩下的就是动机和凶手身份了
Just why and who?
住在对面小屋的那位女士...
The lady in the cottage with a view of the back here...
- 马普尔小姐? - 我要跟她谈谈
- Miss. Marple? - I need to interview her.
你能一起来吗 这些老处女很容易紧张
Would you tag along? These old maids tend to get nervous.
如果你不是很确定的话
If you're not quite sure of something
我会让你慢慢想起来的
I'll wait until you have a little think.
大约6点20分左右
Did you see anyone enter the vicarage
你有没有看见过谁进了寓所?
around 20 past six?
有 普罗瑟罗太太
Yes. Mrs. Protheroe.
你觉得他是那个时候遇害的吗
Is that when you think he was killed?
目前显示是这样
It looks like it.
你听力怎么样
How's your hearing?
非常好
It's excellent.
那你有听到寓所传来的枪响吗
So you would have heard a gun fired from the vicarage?
这说不准 我确实听到了枪响
It's hard to say. I did hear a shot
大概六点半 我还以为是树林传来的
about 6:30 in the woods, I thought,
这并不奇怪 但是
which is not unusual, but...
谁能分辨得清呢
Whether one could tell the difference...
那个画家列丁先生呢
What about this artist, Mr Redding?
嗯 他看上去非常震惊
Well, he looked terribly shocked.
我猜是因为他发现了尸体
I assumed he'd discovered the body.
当然了 他和上校之间
Of course, he and the colonel...
他画过莱蒂斯的泳衣肖像
He'd been painting Lettice,in a bathing suit.
噢 前卫派 是这样叫吧
Oh,avant-garde. Is that the term?
我不相信
I don't believe it.
什么 在牧师寓所里?
What? At the vicarage?
- 是的 夫人 - 安妮?
- Yes, ma'am. - Anne?
卢修斯死了
Lucius is dead.
这是真的吗 豪伊斯先生
Is it really true, Mr Hawes?
- 我在车站听说了 - 是的
- I heard it at the station. - Yes.
我现在正要去牧师寓所
I'm on my way to the vicarage.
- 那里有很多血吧 - 我怎么会知道呢
- Was there much blood? - How would I know that?
不对
No.
你说这会不会是激情犯罪
Do you think it was a crime of passion?
毕竟 普罗瑟罗太太和列丁先生
After all, Mrs Protheroe and Mr Redding...
淫乱必会得到惩罚
Fornication always has consequences,
但我觉得我们不该草率下定论
but I don't think we should jump to conclusions.
上校并不怎么讨人喜欢 对吧
The colonel was not much liked by anyone, was he?
嗯 恐怕是这样
No. I'm afraid not.
当然 他和牧师的会面
Of course, his appointment
也不是什么秘密
with the vicar was hardly a secret.
圣玛丽・米德还能有什么秘密
Are there any secrets in St Mary Mead?
还多着呢 我希望
Lots. Yet. I hope.
我想找人谈谈
I want to talk to someone.
什么时候的事?
When was this?
玛丽没听到些什么吗
Didn't Mary hear anything?
她如常把收音机开到最大声了
Her wireless was turned up full blast as usual.
不 等我到那里后再说
No. Wait till I get there.
但她确实听到上校打了个很响的喷嚏
She did hear the colonel sneeze very loudly.
谁在审讯他 我马上过去
Who's speaking to him? I'll be right there.
作案手法 时间 凶手都齐了
That's how, when and who.
只剩动机了
Now for why
劳伦斯・列丁刚刚去警察局自首了
Lawrence Redding just walked into the station and confessed,
还带了作案凶器
and he's brought the murder weapon.
晚安
Good night.
这里是老屋
Old Hall.
这太可怕了
It is terrible.
当然 我们今天下午就坐火车离开了
We will leave on the afternoon train, of course.
警察知道谁是凶手了吗
Has the police an idea of who could do this thing?
我知道
I have.
是警方的电话 太太
It's the police, madam.
抱歉失陪
Excuse me.
不 警督 不可能 他 我不能
No, Inspector, he can't. He... I can't...
为什么斯莱克警督
Why does Inspector Slack
会认为上校是在6点20分被杀的呢
think the coloneI was shot at 20 past six?
他正好在写便条告诉牧师 他不能再等了
He'd started writing a note to vicar saying he couldn't wait
- 还写上了时间 - 是吗
- He'd put the time on it. - Had he?
而且闹钟刚好停在了6点20分
And the clock stopped at just gone 6:20.
他中弹时把闹钟打到在地上
He knocked it off the desk when he took the bullet.
噢 天啊
Oh, dear.
恐怕我必须去给警督添麻烦了
I'm afraid I must put a cat amongst the Inspector's pigeons.
他一直在讲他的女儿
He was going on and on about his daughter,
但那只是他女儿对我愚蠢的迷恋
which was just her silly little crush,
所以我告诉他
so I told him it was his wife
他该担心的人是他妻子 我只是想让他闭嘴
he had to worry about, just to shut him up.
然后他就暴跳如雷
Then he really started.
我当时想到我这样做 安妮将受到的...
I thought about what I was leaving her to...
于是我就杀了他
and I shot him.
局长让我向您问好
The Chief Constable sends his regards.
真是太有心了
Isn't that lovely?
我偶尔给过他一些帮助
I have been of some assistance to him from time to time.
这点他也说了
He said.
是那个闹钟的问题
It's the clock.
我碰巧知道克莱蒙特太太
I happen to know Mrs Clement
在礼拜日那天 为了牧师能够守时
put it a quarter of an hour fast on Sunday
把闹钟拨快了一刻钟
to improve the vicar's punctuality.
噢 不错 这方法有用吗
Well, wonderful. Did it work?
- 有用 - 那还真不错
- Yes. - I'm glad to hear it.
所以 要么钟真的是在6点5分的时候停了
So, either it was really five past six when it stopped,
而那时上校根本还没抵达寓所
before the colonel even arrived for his appointment,
要么就是凶手为了配合字条上的时间
or the murderer moved the hands back
移动了分针
to match the time on the note.
那个艺术家还是有嫌疑啊
It still fits,the artistic touch.
但列丁先生6点20分的时候在小路上
But Mr Redding was in the lane at 20 past six.
我看到他了
I saw him.
或许你是看到他了 马普尔小姐
You may well have done, Miss Marple,
但他是在6点40分杀的上校
but he killed the colonel at 6.45.
玛丽开门给他的
Mary let him in.
- 牧师也看到他离开了 - 6点45分?
- The vicar saw him leave. - 6:45?
但检验的死亡时间误差不超过十分钟
But I only examined at ten to.
那就是说 他的死亡时间
And told me that he'd died
- 就在那三十分钟之内 - 是的 要我说
- within the last 30 minutes. - At the most, I said.
6点20分或者更早一点 有可能
6:20 or a little before, yes.
6点30分 最多就是6点40分
6:30...6.40 at a pinch,
但若列丁先生说他是在6点45分杀他的话
but if Redding says he shot him at 6:45,
他就是在说谎
he's lying.
那法医就不能有错吗
And doctors are never wrong?
我这有一份自首供词
I've got a confession.
如果上校脑子里的子弹
If the bullet killing the colonel doesn't
和列丁的枪不吻合 我就吃了我的手铐
match Redding's gun, I'll eat my handcuffs.
有时候 事情就是这么简单
Sometimes, the simple explanation is the right one.
昨晚则是个例外
Last night's wasn't.
我会找人送你们出去的
I'll have someone see you out.
如果他是在6点45分中弹的话
If he was shot at a quarter to seven,
为什么他6点20分的那句话
why had he stopped in the middle of a sentence
才写到一半
at 20 past six?
- 安妮 - 我要给警方打电话
- Anne... - I have to telephone the police.
我希望有人陪着我
I'd like someone with me.
- 他是我杀的 - 什么时候杀的
- I killed him. - What time?
马普尔小姐看到我大概是6点20分走的
Miss Marple saw me going at about 20 past six.
我只是
I just...
我只是太恨他了 所以开枪杀了他
I just hated him so much, I shot him.
用什么杀的
With?
他那把旧警枪
His old service revolver
他一直给枪上好子弹 我就拿了
He always kept it loaded and I took it.
安妮 你没有带枪
Anne, you didn't have a gun.
我放在包里了
It was in my bag.
你没有带包
You didn't have a bag.
你穿的那条裙子也藏不了枪
There was nowhere else it could have been, not in that dress
圣玛丽・米德村23...
St Mary Mead 23...
是的 请讲
Yes, speaking.
确定吗
Is that definite?
好的
Right.
我不喜欢浪费时间 普罗瑟罗太太
I don't like my time wasted, Mrs Protheroe.
杀死你丈夫的那颗子弹
The bullet that killed your husband
是从列丁先生的枪里射出的
was fired from Mr Redding's gun.
但他是为了我这样做的
But he did it for me.
他并没有为了谁这样做
He didn't do it for anyone.
我半小时前就释放他了
I released him half an hour ago.
虽然我不相信
He just happened to be carrying his gun
但他只是碰巧带着他的枪
which I don't believe.
更重要的是 这点你也没有想到吧
And more important, and something that you didn't think of,
如果上校是在6点45分被枪杀
if the coloneI was shot at a quarter to seven,
为什么他6点20分的纸条写到一半呢
why did he stop the note like that at 6:20?
- 噢 是啊 - 对吧
- Oh, yes. - Hm-hm.
呃
Er...
- 但如果是他的枪 - 我们会查清楚的
- But if it was his gun... - We'll find out.
他以为我会因谋杀罪而拘捕你
He thinks I'm arresting you for murder.
- 安妮! - 劳伦斯!
- Anne! - Lawrence!
用爱之吻来黏信封?
Sealed with a loving kiss?
这是给我们家弗兰克的
It's to my Frank.
在他不用挖矿劳作的时候
Is he allowed to receive letters
能被允许收信的吗
when he's not breaking rocks?
他才没有在做苦工
He ain't doing hard labour.
但谁能想到呢 列丁先生
Who would have thought it, though? Mr Redding.
这么好的一个年轻人
Such a nice young man.
好到在家里藏着根枪?
Nice enough to keep a gun in the house?
我觉得是普罗瑟罗太太的错
I blame that Mrs Protheroe.
看她到处招摇的样子
The way she swans around.
看那架势 还以为是杂志里面跑出来的呢
You'd think she was in a magazine, the look of her.
依我说 是她让列丁先生这样做的
She put Mr Redding up to it, if you ask me.
麻烦请让一下
Excuse me.
我的足球彩票
My football pools.
世事难料 我上周刚错过了1000英镑
You never know. I only just missed out on ￡1,000 last week.
金钱是一切罪恶的种子
Money is the root of all evil.
那我倒是愿意在花园里种着
I'd give it space in my garden.
再见
Bye.
噢 我还是 我可不想乱说话
Oh, I'd better... I don't want to speak out of turn,
特别是没什么事的话
especially if it wasn't anything.
警察释放了劳伦斯
The police have released Lawrence.
- 列丁先生 - 是吗 那我想
- Mr Redding. - Have they? Then, I wonder...
这一定让你很不安吧
This must be so unsettling for you.
我受不了了
I can't bear it.
我正要去教堂 克莱蒙特太太
I was on my way to the church, Mrs Clement.
要和我一起去祷告吗
Shall we pray together?
呃 我 我要去找查尔斯沃思先生
Erm...I...I need to find Mr Charlesworth
要赶在他关门去吃午餐前
before he closes for lunch.
我需要那些
I need some of those...
噢 随便你们怎么称呼吧 锋利好用的
Oh, whatever you call them! Good and sharp.
普罗瑟罗太太离开我的视线顶多三十秒
Mrs Protheroe was only out of sight for 30 seconds at most
然后她就去了小屋
then she went into the shed.
列丁先生沿小路过去和她见面
Mr Redding joined her from the lane.
他跟我说他要和她道别 他要离开这村子了
He told me he was saying goodbye to her, leaving the village
她一定非常难过
She must have been terribly upset.
他们大概在那里呆了十分钟
They stayed there for ten minutes or so.
教堂的钟响起了半小时报时
The church clock struck a half hour.
他们就出来了 遇上了杜福斯先生
They came out again, meeting Monsieur Dufosse,
他刚好从通向老屋的路走来
who appeared from the footpath to Old Hall.
然后他的孙女也到了
Then his granddaughter arrived.
- 杜福斯? - 恩 普罗瑟罗家的客人
- Dufosse? - Mm. Guests of the Protheroes.
你为什么不把门锁好
You don't keep it shut away?
是 是 我知道我该锁好门
Yes, yes, I know, I know I should.
帮我打扫的塔兰特太太
Mrs Tarrant who mucks me out
总是叫我把门锁好
is always telling me off about that,
而我白天从来不锁门
and I never lock up during the day.
你还记得起
Did you recognise...
在枪出现在书房之前
When was the last time
你最后一次看见它是什么时候吗
you saw the gun before it turned up in the study?
呃 前天吧
Erm...the day before yesterday.
你能认出那个声音
Did you recognise the voice...
你不用让你的脚踝休息一下吗 马普尔小姐
Wouldn't you prefer to rest your ankle, Miss Marple?
不用了 谢谢关心 你能认出电话里的声音吗
No, thank you. Did you recognise the voice on the telephone?
不 电话里说如果不想让卢修斯知道我俩的事
No. It just said to come straight over to the vicarage
就直接过去牧师寓所
if I didn't want Lucius to find out about us.
- 男的还是女的 - 我想是女的
- A man or woman? - A woman. I think.
听起来很模糊
It did sound quite faint
就像是那人把话筒握得很远
as if someone was holding the receiver away from them.
所以也可能是个男的
So it could have been a man.
明察秋毫嘛 牧师
Well spotted, Vicar.
谁会知道你当时在马普尔小姐家
Who knew you were at Miss Marple's?
没有谁啊
No one.
那人一定是看到我在那
Someone must have seen me arrive.
呃 监视着我
Er...watching me.
我丈夫也死了 我
My husband's dead. I...
就是说 你穿过花园 来到落地窗前
So, you came through the garden, and up to the French windows
之后发生了什么事
and then what happened?
是的 窗子是开着的 但我没听到什么声音
Yes, they were open, but I didn't hear any voices.
我看到屋里没有人 所以就去了小屋
I looked in and no-one was here, so I went up to the shed
去看能不能找到劳伦斯
to see if I could find Lawrence.
屋里没有人 那不可能啊
No one here? That's impossible.
你有走进去吗
Did you come right in?
没有 我只是 伸头往里看了下
No. I just...popped my head in.
啊 这可真是世上最大的一叶兰了
Ah. It's the biggest aspidistra in the world.
如果上校是坐在书桌这边
If the coloneI was here at the desk
是死是活 你都是看不到他的
you wouldn't have seen him alive or dead.
坐下吧
Sit down.
你去蓝野猪旅馆喝了一杯
A drink at the Blue Boar
然后又回来找牧师
then you returned to see the vicar again
说说你的状况 然后呢
about your situation, and then what?
这次该说实话了
The authorised version this time.
我走进去 他已经死了 我看到了我的枪
I came in. He was dead. I saw my gun.
我还以为是安妮终于受够他了
I thought that Anne had finally had enough
所以我捡起了枪
so I picked it up
然后就离开了
and I left.
之后你为了保护她去自首
And you confessed to protect her.
然后你又用这招去保护他
And you returned the favour
因为你以为真是他做的
because you thought he'd done it.
多么浪漫的爱情故事
Very love's young dream.
我猜你们俩每周五都去看话剧吧
I bet you two are down the Odeon every Friday.
告诉你的客人 我要跟他们谈话
Tell your guests I need to speak to them.
除非我同意
Don't think about
不然他们别想能离开这村子 走吧
leaving this village until I say so. Go.
呃 抱歉
Erm... Sorry.
麻烦让一下
Excuse me.
你不喜欢克莱蒙特先生 对吧
You don't like Mr Clement, do you?
没有针对他
Nothing personal.
只是 牧师们总让我想起婚姻
Vicars in general...remind me of marriage.
- 啊 当然了 - 当然什么
- Ah...of course. - Of course what?
哈特内尔小姐表姐的女仆
Miss Hartnell's cousin's maid
正在和来自梅尔切斯特的屠夫儿子约会
is just walking out with a butcher's boy from Melchester
这让你的岳母很受打击
who delivers to your mother-in-Law.
斯莱克太太已经和她相处了
Mrs Slack has been staying with her for a...
有一个小假期了吧 算起来
little holiday, I gather.
到目前为止 是两个月又六天的小假期了
A little two-month six-day holiday, so far.
- 噢 天啊 - 嗯
- Oh, dear. - Hm.
当然了
Of course
我只听说了克莱蒙特先生对那通假电话的说法
I've only got Mr Clement's word about the bogus call.
当然 你不会怀疑他吧?
Surely you don't suspect him?
- 呃 - 我可以看看吗
- Erm... - May I?
当然
Please.
6点20分
6:20.
"恐怕我不能再等了"
"I'm afraid I cannot wait for you any longer."
上校他 确实不是很有耐心的人
The colonel was...not the most patient of men,
但如果是6点20分的话
but the vicar would only have been
牧师也不过是迟了五分钟啊
five minutes late at 20 past six.
在上校进门的时候 玛丽也提醒过了
Mary had warned him he wouldn't be on time
牧师会晚一点回来
when she showed him in.
嗯 6点20分
Hm. 6:20.
你不觉得 这个墨水是
The ink is...don't you think,
蓝黑色的
blue-black,
而不是蓝色的吗
rather than blue?
- 是啊 字也相对小一点 - 嗯
- Yes, and the writing's smaller. - Mm.
谢谢你 马普尔小姐
Thank you, Miss Marple.
那就是说 他可能是6点20分之后被杀的
That means he could have been shot after 6:20,
而字条上的时间是凶手加上去的
and then the murderer put that onto the note
凶手还把闹钟拨到
and then altered the clock...
拨到普罗瑟罗太太接完那通匿名电话
...to the time when Mrs Protheroe came here
来到书房时的时间
in answer to her anonymous telephone call.
并且用列丁先生的枪做凶器
And Mr Redding's gun as the murder weapon.
我想他们是被 呃
I think they were being...er...
设计成替罪羔羊了
...set up as pasties.
替罪羔羊 确实
Patsies...it is.
嗯
Mm.
谢谢你 警督
Thank you, Inspector.
抱歉 抱歉 我待会再过来 我是来找些
Sorry. Sorry, I'll come back. I was looking for some...
你坐的正好是他被杀的位置 对吧
You're exactly where he was killed, aren't you?
真是可怕 你们知道谁是凶手了吗
How horrible. Do you know who did it?
不 还没有
Not yet, no.
主说"伸冤在我 我必报应"
"'Vengeance is mine. I will repay,' saith the Lord."
但看来有人比主抢先了一步
Well, someone beat the Lord to it.
我要倒些水 该吃药了
I need some water. For my medicine.
但如果他是6点30分被杀的
But supposing he was killed at 6:30?
那就和你听到的那下枪声吻合了
That would tie in with the shot that you heard.
如果枪声是从这里传来的话
If it was from here.
你确定在6点20分的时候
You're sure the only person you saw come in
你只看到过普罗瑟罗太太进去吗
was Mrs Protheroe at 6:20?
从花园进去的话 我确定
Through the garden, certainly
但是从我的小屋没办法看到落地窗
but I can't see the French windows from my cottage.
而且树木也在这边挡着视线
and the woods come right up on this side.
虽然有点麻烦 但如果凶手早有预谋
It would be a scramble, but if one was determined
或者凶手从前厅进来的
or if one came in through the hall.
上校耳朵不好使
The colonel was deaf,
那他们就可以偷偷地躲在他后面
so they could creep up behind him.
前厅?不 不可能
The hall? No, no
这样就需要玛丽给他们开大门了
cos Mary would have let them in the front door.
她没有告诉你这门通常是开着的吗
Hasn't she told you it's often left open?
玛丽!
Mary!
你自己能行吗
Is this wise?
你并不擅长园艺
You're not exactly green-fingered.
噢 别大惊小怪的 亲爱的 相信我
Oh, don't fuss, darling! Trust me.
把那本剪刀一样的东西递给我 好吗
Pass those scissory things, would you?
牧师收
伦?
Len?
不好意思
Sorry.
谢谢 哎呦
Thank you. Ooh!
但要免淫乱的事 男子当各有自己的妻子 女子也当各有自己的丈夫
看好你的妻子 第七章 第二节
WATCH YOUR WIFE CHAPTER 7 VERSE 2
- 噢 - 抱歉吓到你了 莱蒂斯
- Oh! - Sorry to startle you, Lettice.
- 对你的遭遇 我深表同情 - 噢 是的
- You have my deepest sympathy. - Oh. Yes.
嗯 你发现自己身上沾到颜料了吗
Mm. Do you know you've got some paint on you?
很久之前沾上的了 我要让人洗干净才行
That's been there ages. I must have it cleaned.
你有看到一顶黄色的贝雷帽吗
You haven't seen a yellow beret?
- 没有 - 我很确定我漏在这里了
- No. - I'm sure I left it in here last week
- 上星期来找丹尼斯的时候 - 我很遗憾
- when I came to see Dennis. - I'm sorry.
你?做园艺?
You? Gardening?
我总得找点事情做吧
Well, I have to do something.
- 你昨天买什么回来了 - 什么
- What did you bring back yesterday? - Hm?
- 从伦敦啊 - 噢 是的 伦敦
- From London. - Oh, yes, London.
- 我没找到合心的 - 这可不像你啊
- I couldn't find a thing I wanted. - Not like you.
- 再见 - 再见
- Bye. - Bye.
我和摄影师私下谈过了
I had a man-to-man word with the photographer.
- 他说会寄给我 - 嘘 让我好好看看你
- He said he'd send me - Shh! Let me just look at you.
- 他明天就准备收拾离开了 - 真遗憾
- He'll start clearing it out tomorrow. - It's a shame.
他已经开始捕捉到我的神韵了 你说呢
He was on his way to getting me. Don't you think?
是吗
Was he?
噢 你这个傻瓜
Oh, you silly man!
的确 他是有魅力
Yes, he's charming,
的确  他就像是拂过田野的一缕清风
yes, he's like a breath of fresh air in the village
的确 他也逗过我高兴 不过
yes, I was flattered, but...
不可能的
no.
你才是我的丈夫 伦
You are my husband, Len.
我永远不会欺骗你的
I would never deceive you.
除非是善意的
Unless it was for the best.
后脑处有一处枪伤
There was a single bullet wound to the back of the head,
我推断这就是死因
which I concluded was the cause of death.
你能给出死亡时间的正式估计吗 海多克医生
Did you fomarlly estimate the time of death, Dr Haydock?
大概是在6点20分到6点40分之间
Between 6:20 or thereabouts and 6.40 at the latest.
谢谢你
Thank you
我在6点15分开门给他后 就回到了厨房
I showed him in at 6:15 and then went back to the kitchen.
但他看起来似乎很高兴
He wasn't half looking pleased with himself
就像猫捉到老鼠一样
though, like the cat that got the cream.
大概五分钟之后 我听到
Then I heard him give a blooming great sneeze
他打了个响嚏
about five minutes after,
再后来我见到他时
and the next time I see him,
他已经死了
he was dead.
很好 希尔小姐 下去吧
Very well, Miss Hill. Step down.
你知道是上校判她未婚夫入狱的吗
Did you know the colonel sent her young man to prison?
弗兰克・塔兰特
Frank Tarrant.
最后 普罗瑟罗太太 你能想到
Lastly, Mrs Protheroe, can you think of anyone
有谁会想杀害你丈夫的吗
who might have wished your husband harm?
不 恐怕我想不出
No. No-one at all, I'm afraid.
- 谢谢你 - 但是
- Thank you. - Although...
- 请讲 - 礼拜一在梅尔切斯特商业街上
- Yes? - On Monday in Melchester High Street,
他差点被一辆摩托车给撞了
he was nearly hit by a motorcycle.
你是想说那是故意的?
Are you suggesting this was deliberate?
当时看起来倒不像是
It didn't seem so at the time.
我只是觉得我应该提一下
I just thought I should mention it.
我判定死者
I find that the deceased
卢修斯・亚历山大・普罗瑟罗上校
Colonel Lucius Alexander Protheroe,
是被未知的一人或多人所谋杀
was murdered by a person or persons unknown.
你怀疑那辆摩托车有问题吗
Did you wonder about the motorbike?
我想它只是开得过快了
It was just going too fast, I thought.
但他当时确实就差一点儿
He did come very close, though.
他还是她 谁说得准呢
He or she. One couldn't tell.
话说回来 礼拜二下午
By the way, when the colonel
上校在梅尔切斯特呆了那么晚
stayed late in Melchester on Tuesday afternoon,
他在做什么呢
what was he doing?
我想 是去见罗斯・哈金斯太太吧
Meeting Mrs Ross-Harkins, I think.
赫麦亚妮吗 她是主教的妻子
Hermione? The bishop's wife,
也是他的法官同僚
and his fellow magistrate too.
警督 请你一定要找出凶手
Inspector, please find out who did this.
如果有人故意陷害
If someone tried to make it look as if...
那他们一定是很恨我和劳伦斯 而且 呃
Well, they must hate Lawrence and me very much, and er...
嗯 我很害怕
Well, I'm scared.
等一下
Wait.
噢
Oh.
这是在落地窗外面找到的
This was outside the French windows.
牧师家没人抽烟
No one at the vicarage smokes.
- 是丹尼斯偷偷藏的吧 - 你闻下
- Dennis sneaking a crafty one? - Sniff.
法国的 很久之前 去休假的年轻人
French. Young men on leave a long time ago
他们会从法国带这个回来
they'd bring them back from France.
我怀疑 杜福斯先生从小路走出来的时候
When Monsieur Dufosse appeared on the footpath,
是不是刚从树林里出去的
I wonder if he'd only just turned into it from the woods.
你看 事情发生之后
Look, it's easy to imagine
很容易会有各种各样的猜想
all kinds of things after the event,
但是事情其实很简单
but the simple fact is...
谋杀从来不简单
Murder is never simple.
如果我们放弃任何线索 那就太愚笨了
We would be foolish, stupid, to ignore any possibility.
我们?
We?
我说了我们吗
Did I say that?
真是抱歉
So sorry.
我也不知道该送她一盒巧克力
I don't know whether to buy her a box of chocs
还是踢开她的拐杖
or kick away her stick.
我更喜欢巧克力
I'd prefer the chocolates.
你没有穿黑色真是太棒了 那太沮丧了
How marvellous that you're not in black. It's so dreary.
- 我该认识你吗 - 我想让你认识
- Should I know you? - I want you to.
- 你是谁 - 啊 "西尔维娅是谁
- Who are you? - Ah."Who is Sylvia?
她是什么样的人呢"
What is she?"
我们来慢慢聊
Let's have a little chat.
我沿着小路散了一会步
I made a walk along the footpath.
景色很美丽
It is very beautiful.
你有进去过树林吗 杜福斯先生
Did you go into the woods, Mr Dufosse?
没有 只是在小路上散步
No. Footpath only.
你什么时候回去法国
When do you go back to France?
我们现在已经误了搭联运车的时间
We have missed the good connection now.
明天坐首班火车离开
Tomorrow by the first train.
我可能还需要联系你们
I might need to get in touch with you.
你们的杂志社叫什么名字
What's this magazine of yours called?
麻烦把它拼出来
You'll have to spell it.
主教和他太太明天才能回来吗
And the bishop and his wife get back tomorrow?
麻烦转告赫麦亚妮 让他们一回到
Would you please be kind to ask Hermione to telephone me
梅尔切斯特就给我打个电话
as soon as they get back to Melchester?
我是简・马普尔
Jane Marple.
或许 是的
It might, yes.
的确是非常重要
Very important indeed.
安妮拿到了屋子
Anne gets the hall.
但你也可以自己安顿下来
But you can set up on your own.
我会帮你找地方的
I'll help you look for somewhere.
他才去世了两天
He's only been dead two days.
所以呢 你讨厌他啊
So? You hated him.
- 凶手是在帮你忙呢 - 丹尼斯
- The killer did you a favour. - Dennis!
- 我说的是实话 - 我会回屋了
- It's true. - I'm going in.
为什么你跟马普尔小姐说你丢了贝雷帽
Why did you tell Miss Marple you lost your beret?
打网球的时候 你还带着呢
You had it at tennis.
你在偷听吗
Were you listening?
而且我们还没打完 你就离开了
And you left before we finished the game.
你也很快就走了 园丁告诉我的
And you went soon after. The gardener told me.
是啊 但你总不会觉得我会杀了你父亲吧
Yes. But you don't think I could have killed your father.
你总不会觉得我会那么关心你吧
You don't think I care enough about you.
- 我知道是谁杀的 - 你们在这里啊
- I know who did it. - There you are.
真是一石二鸟
Two birds, one stone.
或许你们能给我说说
Perhaps you could tell me
你们周二傍晚都在哪里呢
where you both were on Tuesday evening.
我们在一起打网球
Together. We played tennis.
然后一起去树林散步了
Then we went for a walk. In the woods.
是啊 去了树林 走得挺远
Yes, the woods, rolling around
差不多都走到本哈姆镇了 真是个美好的夜晚
over towards Much Benham. It was a smashing evening.
对吧
Wasn't it?
你好 托尼对吧 我是琼・哈格里夫斯
Hello, Tony? It's Joan Hargreaves.
我需要你帮忙 你那里离圣玛丽・米德村近吗
I need a favour. Is your place anywhere near St Mary Mead?
我把账本放在书桌上了
I left the ledgers on the desk
这样上校一来 你就可以交给他
so you'd have them to hand when the colonel arrived.
你想会不会是被 凶手拿走了
You don't think the...murderer took them?
不会 我想只是玛丽乱动东西罢了
No. I expect Mary's been moving things.
话说回来 帐目都整理好了吧
Were they all in order, by the way?
普赖斯・里德利太太那张一磅的钞票
Mrs Price-Ridley's pound note was counted in
算到了义卖的钱里了
with the jumble sale money.
我回查了过去六个月的帐目
I went back over the last six months
帐面都是平的
and everything balances.
正如我们所说的一样
As we knew it would.
"私欲生出罪
"Lust bringeth forth sin
而罪生出死"
and sin bringeth forth death."
我 我不能再呆下去了
I...I can't stay in here.
我不知道该怎么做
I don't know what to do.
突然之间 我们就似乎冷淡了
Suddenly, we just seem so...distant.
你想要怎么做呢
What would you like to do?
噢
Oh...
离开这里 只有我们两个
Walk away, just the two of us
一起迎接清新飘雪的早晨
into a crisp and snowy morning.
然后以此作画
Then paint it.
玛丽听到的喷嚏声
The sneeze that Mary heard
有可能是凶手发出的 对吧
that could have been the murderer, couldn't it?
而安妮当时在场
And Anne was there.
我只希望她平安无事
I just hope she's safe.
你朋友早到了 很好
He is early, your friend. Good.
晚安啊
Bonjour.
你们工作的杂志社战前就倒闭了
The magazine you work for went out of business before war.
好了 你们都拿走了什么 银器吗
Now, what have you got? The silver?
我孙子 恩里
My grandson, Henri.
他本会成为我的丈夫
He would have been my husband.
我们在1943年相识
We met in 1943
他当时在抵抗部队
He was in the Resistance.
那你呢 哈格里夫斯小姐
And you, Miss Hargreaves?
特别行动队
Special Operations.
我被投派到法国 和恩里与他的部队一起工作
I was dropped into France, working with Henri and his crew.
- 上校呢 - 他在伦敦进行指挥工作
- The colonel? - He commanded a desk in London.
他背叛了恩里
Il a trahi Henri.
- 他背叛了他 - 他背叛了我的孙子
- He betrayed him. - He betrayed my grandson.
普罗瑟罗的部门负责
Protheroe's section was responsible
提供我们地区所有的物资
for supplying the whole of our region,
武器 雷管等等
weapons, detonators and so on.
1944年伊始 他必须进行一次投钱行动
Early in'44, he had to organise a money drop
数目上万的法郎现金
tens of thousands of francs in cash.
恩里和我在他给出的地点等待
Henri and I waited at the rendezvous he'd given us,
但飞机飞过去了
but the plane went over
然后在一里外的地方投落了
and dropped the canister a mile away.
- 为什么 - 他给的地点是错的
- Why? - The rendezvous was false.
钱被一个叫拉科姆的男人拿走了
The money was picked up by a man called Lacombe,
他是组织的一员 战前就认识普罗瑟罗
one of our group, who had known Protheroe before the war.
就因为单纯的贪欲
It was simple greed.
战后 他们分了赃
After the war, they divided it between them.
拉科姆和上校
Lacombe and the colonel.
去年拉科姆在死之前向我坦白了
Lacombe made a confession to me, last year when he was dying
这就是证据 银行转账单 银行结单
That's the proof: bank transfers, statements
拉科姆收到的指示
Lacombe's instructions.
那恩里怎么了
What happened to Henri?
拉科姆向德军透露了我们的行踪
Lacombe had tipped off the Germans
他们找到了我们
and they came for us.
我逃了出来
I escaped.
- 他却没有 - 他被折磨至死
- He did not. - He was tortured...until death.
我的亲孙子
My grandson.
- 我很遗憾 - 我也是
- I'm very sorry. - And so am I.
我也是 我跟你说实话
So am I. I'll tell you the truth.
我是要去杀了那个混蛋上校的
I had to kill that son of a bitch, the colonel!
因为他 于是
Because of him. And so,
我带上我的手枪 走过树林
I got my pistol, I went to the woods,
走到了牧师寓所
up to the vicarage,
穿过落地窗 走进了书房
through the French windows and into the study.
- 啊 - 然后呢 杜福斯先生?
- Ah... - Yes, Mr Dufosse?
我去晚了
I was too late.
我去得太他妈晚了
I was too damn late!
他死了
He was dead.
- 你是说? - 我是说
- Are you saying...? - I'm saying...
他已经死了
he was already dead.
谢谢老天
Thankfully.
你很会做家务嘛
You're quite good at this.
- 我必须得学会 - 噢
- I've had to learn - Oh
所以说 如果他所说的是真的
So,if what he told you is true,
上校在6点30分前就死了
the colonel was dead by 6:30
那时杜福斯先生和其他人会合了
when Monsieur Dufosse joined the others.
恰好 如果你听到的那下响声正是谋杀枪声
Only just, if the shot you heard was the murder.
- 你相信他所说的吗 - 是的
- Do you believe him? - Yes.
但是奇怪的是
But the interesting thing is
杜福斯在书房所看到的
what Monsieur Dufosse saw in the study.
他形容枪的枪筒很长
He described the gun as having a long barrel,
你知道的 像老式西部片那种
you know, like the old Wild West ones?
而且他看到的便条
And he thought the note
有大半页那么长 而不是只有几行
was a good half page long, not just a couple of lines.
这可真奇怪了
That is interesting.
但我不确定他的话有几分可信
I don't know how reliable he is, though.
他当时刚从强光的户外进入屋内
He had just come in out of bright sunlight...
而且他年纪也大了
..and he is getting on.
你漏了一点没洗
You've missed a bit.
那便条
The note...
你给普罗瑟罗太太看过了吗
Have you shown it to Mrs Protheroe?
不 还没有
No, actually.
我想 她正在牧师寓所里呢
She's at the vicarage now, I believe.
安排丧事
Funeral arrangements.
时间和文字都不是他的笔迹
Neither is in his writing, not the time or the words.
我不明白
I don't understand.
现在这个调查阶段 大家都糊涂了
You're not alone at this stage of the investigation.
你有上校的字迹模板吗
Do you have any examples of the colonel's handwriting?
当然
Yes, of course.
我昨天在书桌下面找到的
I found it yesterday under the desk.
这不是格丽泽尔达的
It's not Griselda's.
这是安妮的
It's Anne's.
- 我应该交给警督吗 - 不用
- Should I give it to the Inspector? - No.
现在还不用
Not just yet.
长官 我能跟你说几句吗
Sir, can I have a word?
真是令人不快
How very unpleasant.
那一节是什么
The verse?
"但要免淫乱的事 男子当各有自己的妻子
"To avoid fornication, let every man have his own wife
女子也当各有自己的丈夫"
"and let every woman have her own husband."
摩托车是在当天早上被盗的
The motorbike was stolen in the morning
事故之后就被丢弃了
and dumped soon after the incident.
这谋杀手段真是太粗鲁 太难捉摸了
Such a...crude and uncertain way of killing someone,
- 除非这只是用来吓唬他的 - 我 呃
- unless it was just meant to frighten him. - I, er...
我必须继续走访了
I must get on with my visiting.
我就不用送了
I can...see myself out.
我们要回去找普罗瑟罗太太了
We'll get back to Mrs Protheroe.
你好 马普尔小姐
Hello, Miss Marple.
我在想把这幅画留下来
I was thinking about leaving this one.
或许某天 我会回来完成它
I might come back and finish it one day.
你什么时候走?
When do you go?
还没定 明天或者后天
I don't know. Tomorrow or the next day.
我一收拾完小屋就走了
As soon as I can clean out the cottage.
回去伦敦吗
Back to London?
我在考虑去爱尔兰
I was thinking about Ireland.
让我们俩分开得彻底点
Put some real distance between us.
你终会开始新生活的
You'll find a new life in time.
- 但安妮不会 对吧 - 我会尽力帮她的
- But Anne won't, will she? - I'll do my best for her.
她是个好朋友
She's a good friend.
谢谢你 谢谢你所做的一切
Thank you. Thank you for everything.
你在哭吗
You've been crying?
沏茶熏的 亲爱的
Pot and kettle, dear.
我是来和你商量的
I have some things to discuss.
用你熏香的便笺 这可不明智啊
Not very clever to use your scented notepaper.
人们的底线都在哪了 这是我所担心的
Where are people's standards? That's what worries me.
在梅尔切斯特
This young man
克莱蒙特太太被看到和一个年轻人在一起
Mrs Clement was seen with in Melchester...
哈特内尔小姐说他非常英俊
Miss Hartnell said he was rather handsome
还送了花给她
and he gave her flowers.
即使是这样 我也肯定她是有合理解释的
I'm sure there's an innocent explanation, but even so,
说真的 玛乔丽...
really, Marjorie...
我很羞愧 简
I'm so ashamed, Jane.
布鲁斯会怎么看我呢 还有安德鲁?
What would Bruce think of me? And Andrew?
他们会知道你只是寂寞而已
That you sometimes get very lonely.
- 是的 - 说起安妮・普罗瑟罗的底线
- Yes. - And Anne Protheroe's standards...
当然 你打电话到我家里找她的时候
Of course, you weren't to know the colonel had been murdered
并不知道上校已经被谋杀了吧
when you telephoned her at my cottage, but even so,
但即使这样 这还是让她陷入了困境
it put her in a difficult position when she went over there.
那不是我干的
That wasn't me!
- 葬礼什么时候举行 - 周二下午
- When's the funeral? - Tuesday afternoon.
啊 我那天一上午都在伦敦
Ah. I'm in London all morning.
我希望列车会比上周二好点
I hope the trains are better than last Tuesday.
我不得不求搭顺风车回来
I had to cadge a lift back.
谋杀案那天吗
The day of the murder?
简直一团糟 一下午都没有一班
Chaos. Not a single train
回圣玛丽・米德村的列车
to St Mary Mead the whole afternoon.
我们每撒一个谎
Every time we tell a lie...
都是对上帝的不敬
..we are offending God.
"人心比万物都诡诈
"The heart is deceitful above all things,
坏到极处
and desperately wicked.
谁能识透呢?"
Who can know it?"
上帝可以
Well, God can.
他鉴察人心 识人肺腑
He sees into our hearts and searches them,
依照各人所作所为
to give every man according to his ways
以及他的行事后果给予奖惩
and according to the fruit of his doings.
那么 让我们保持纯洁的心灵
Let us, then, keep our hearts pure
待我们与使徒保罗相见时 便可说
so we may say with Paul,
"在上帝面前 我一生心存良知"
"I have lived in all good conscience before God."
- 噢 真不走运 - 不关运气的事
- Oh, bad luck. - It wasn't luck.
有人故意刺破我的轮胎
Someone stabbed my tyre.
真是粗暴至极
Such a violent thing to do.
这些天来坏事接踵而至
With everything that's been going on, I'm...
我真是害怕 列丁先生
I'm terrified, Mr Redding.
如果你乐意 我就陪你走回家吧
Well, I'll walk you to your digs if you'd like.
噢 好啊 你真愿意吗
Oh, yes, please. Would you?
愿上帝保佑你
Bless you.
谢谢你
Thank you.
什么事?
Yes?
我想要
I want to...
心存良知地活着
live in all good conscience.
请让我向你介绍
May I introduce you
我的母亲
to my mother
我知道 我知道我不是一个好母亲的模范
I know. I know I'm not a good advertisement for motherhood.
我又不需要什么模范妈妈
I don't want an advertisement.
容我冒犯 为什么上校要和你离婚呢
Why did the colonel divorce you, may I ask?
我有过那么一点点的放纵
I had a...tiny, tiny fling.
我乐衷于派对和社交
I like parties and people,
但是卢修斯想要管着我
but Lucius wanted to clip my wings.
他答应给我零用钱 条件是
He offered me an allowance in return...
条件是永远不再见我
In return for never seeing me again.
直到现在
Until now.
我第二任丈夫去世六年之后
It's taken me six years
我才能鼓起勇气
since my second husband died to get my courage up.
多半不过是些酒后之勇罢了
Dutch courage, mostly.
我并不为自己骄傲
I'm not very proud of myself.
至少你现在在这儿 妈妈
You're here now, Mother.
我还以为你死了呢
I thought you were dead.
先别说这些无谓感伤了
Never mind the hearts and flowers.
听我说 我们有目击证人看到
Look, when Protheroe came to your room...
普罗瑟罗去过你的房间 当时你是否要勒索他
We have a witness. Were you trying to blackmail him?
天啊 不 这可真是冤枉
Lord, no! I'm very well set up.
不 我只是告诉他
No. I just told him
我想见我可爱的女儿莱蒂斯
I wanted to see lovely daughter Lettice.
她会让我改过自新的
She's going to reform me.
我现在只有你了
You're all I've got.
她希望我住在小屋里
She sees me in a cottage,
有空就烘培果酱或者编织 之类的
baking jam and knitting...things.
要是我们有空能去旅游一下就好了 亲爱的
As long as we can have an occasional cruise, dear.
莱蒂斯
Lettice...
我能私下和你讲几句吗
may I have a private word?
- 这是安妮的 - 这是在你父亲被谋杀的
- It's Anne's. - It was under the desk
书桌下面找到的
where your father was murdered.
我就知道是她杀的 告诉警方吧
I knew it was her. Tell the police.
是不是那天你假装
Did you put it there
找贝雷帽的时候放在那里的?
when you were pretending to look for your beret?
案发当天她并没戴着这对耳环
She wasn't wearing those earrings on the day of the murder.
- 没有吗 - 噢 莱蒂斯这可是我啊
- Wasn't she? - Oh, Lettice, it's me.
好吧 但是我觉得
All right, but I don't see
这有什么大不了的 马普尔小姐
what difference it makes, Miss Marple.
反正就是她杀的
She killed him somehow
这样她就可以和劳伦斯在一起了
so she could get her hands on Lawrence.
- 莱蒂斯- 怎么了
- Lettice - What?
你裙子上的红色颜料是新弄的吧
The red paint on your dress was new, wasn't it?
你之前就躲在那间小屋里
You'd just been in the shed.
那又怎样 我听到你们过来了 我得躲起来啊
So? I heard you all coming and I had to hide.
我肯定是碰到什么东西了
I must have brushed against something.
但是 这叫洋红色
It was magenta, anyway.
激情的颜色 劳伦斯说的
The colour of passion, Lawrence says.
要知道 赫麦亚妮 我必须要告诉警察
You know, Hermione, I'll have to tell the police.
谢谢你 亲爱的
Thank you, dear.
当上校如约来到牧师寓所时
When the colonel kept his appointment at the vicarage,
他刚好得知豪伊斯先生
he had just learnt
是因为受到怀疑而离开上一任教区的
that Mr Hawes left his last parish under a cloud.
主教没有告诉牧师是想再给他一次机会
The bishop kept it from the vicar to give him another chance
- 他做了什么 - 做假帐
- What had he done? - Fiddled the accounts.
罗尼自杀了
Ronnie's tried to kill himself.
海多克医生正在那里
Dr Haydock's there
他还发现了普罗瑟罗上校
and he's found a statement
所写的指责他的信
from Colonel Protheroe accusing him...
- 指责他挪用捐款吗 - 是的
- Accusing him of stealing? - Yes.
我欠你一盒巧克力
I owe you a box of chocs.
什么都瞒不过你 对吧 马普尔小姐
Nothing gets past you, Miss Marple, does it?
几乎没有过
Hardly ever.
什么都瞒不过你 对吧 马普尔小姐
Nothing gets past you, Miss Marple, does it?
几乎没有过 年轻人
Hardly ever, young man.
真是狡猾
How clever!
真是恶毒
How wicked!
煤气开到最大档
The gas was full on,
大量镇静剂会让他安静入眠
and that much sedative would have put him to sleep quickly.
再迟几分钟 他就真能逃过绞刑了
Another few minutes and he would have cheated the hangman.
"今日关于圣玛丽・米德村助理牧师
"Note of conversation today regarding Ronald Hawes
罗纳德・豪伊斯先前
curate of St Mary Mead.
挪用资金的谈话记录" 都在这里了
Previous embezzlement of funds..." It's all here.
杜福斯先生说过他看到的便条篇幅更长
Monsieur Dufosse said the note he saw was longer.
那套账本 他说过他留在了书房里
The accounts. He told me he'd left them in the study.
劳伦斯・列丁或许知道他的精神状态
Lawrence Redding can tell us his state of mind.
女房东说他们一起进来的 还聊了一下
The landlady said he came in with him and stayed talking.
- 现在跑起来很好 对吧 - 噢
- Running well now, isn't she? - Ooh.
我都明白了 警督
I've got it, Inspector.
莱蒂斯说的没错
Lettice was right.
安妮・普罗瑟罗确实杀害了她的丈夫
Anne Protheroe did kill her husband.
安妮和劳伦斯・列丁
Anne and Lawrence Redding.
他们确保使奸情曝光
They made themselves the obvious suspects
让自己成为最明显的嫌疑人
by ensuring their secret was out,
他们知道如果计划成功
knowing that if their plan worked
他们之后就能摆脱嫌疑了
They would later appear above suspicion
噢 我忘了你要过来
Oh! I forgot you were coming.
当然啦 他并没有忘记
Which, of course, he had not,
而安妮提议换个地方 改去三角帽酒馆
and Anne Protheroe chose the Toby Jug just for a change
列丁先生并不是要撞倒上校
Mr Redding wasn't trying to run the colonel down
他知道 当安妮在审讯时提及此事
He knew it would help them muddy the waters
这有助他们扰乱调查方向
when Anne mentioned it at the inquest.
- 该死的蠢蛋! - 噢
- Bloody fool! - Oh!
他们是要确保我会成为
They were making sure I'd be a captive audience
他们这个把戏的忠实观众
for their little charade in a ringside seat
那时他身上一定带着枪和消音器
He must have had his gun with him then and a silencer
还记得杜福斯先生说到的长枪筒吗
Monsieur Dufosse, remember, spoke of a long barrel.
列丁先生在书房等你
Mr Redding in the study.
这是正确的决定
It's the right decision.
- 你跟她说了吗 - 我还没想到怎么说
- Have you told her? - I need to find the words.
之后 他打了两个电话
Then, he made two telephone calls,
第一个假装艾博特先生的邻居
the first to get the vicar out of the way
让牧师离开寓所
by pretending to be Mr Abbot's neighbour
玛丽 低地农场的老艾博特先生
Mary, old Mr Abbot at Lower Farm
他邻居来电说他又病重垂危了
his neighbour's telephoned to say he's very poorly again.
第二个打到我的家里
The second to my cottage.
圣玛丽・米德村235号
St Mary Mead 235.
一切就绪 亲爱的
We're all set, darling.
那是找我的 失陪了
It was for me. Sorry.
她知道我会证明她身上不可能有枪
She knew I'd see she couldn't possibly have a gun with her
在6点20分 她去了牧师寓所
when she went into the vicarage at 20 past six
就在那个时候 你射杀了你的丈夫
Which was when you shot your husband.
你电话里还说是让我来品尝咖啡蛋糕呢
"Coffee and cake," you said, when you telephoned.
劳伦斯在哪里
Where's Lawrence.
现在已经被逮捕了
Under arrest by now.
玛丽在6点20分听到的响嚏
The loud sneeze that Mary heard at 6:20
是你的消音手枪发出的
was your silenced pistol
而开枪的人是普罗瑟罗太太 列丁先生
Mr Redding, fired by Mrs Protheroe.
6点30分的枪声一直让我迷惑
The shot at 6:30 had me puzzled,
直到马普尔小姐发现了她的所为
until Miss Marple found what she did.
枪声不是从树林或寓所传来的
It didn't come from the woods or from the house
而是你的木屋里
It came from the shed.
于是她和杜福斯家的人一起离开
So she goes off with the Dufosses
而你去了蓝野猪旅馆
and you go to the Blue Boar
要大杯的 我今天过得糟透了
A large one. I've had a hell of a day.
之后你返回牧师寓所
Then you return to the vicarage
借口说要再见一次克莱蒙特先生
on the pretext of seeing Mr Clement again
而你明知他正在瞎忙活 根本还没回来
knowing he wouldn't be back from his wild-goose chase.
跟上校一起在书房等吧
Wait in the study with the colonel.
- 他也在吗 - 是的
- He's here? - He is.
你带走了凶器
You remove the murder weapon
还留下了一张故意留下破绽的假便条
and leave a forged note with deliberate mistakes.
纸条是你之前从牧师寓所里拿的
Different handwriting in different inks
用不同的墨水和笔迹来写
on vicarage notepaper you'd taken previously.
出乎意料地看到了上校写的陈述信
A shock to find a statement from the colonel
但这日后或许能派上用场
but it might come in useful
你知道钟是调快的 你重调了时间
You reset the clock knowing it was fast
这一切都是为了让我们相信
all to make us think Mrs Protheroe
普罗瑟罗太太与他丈夫的死
was being falsely implicated
毫无牵连
in her husband's murder
而上校的陈述信在昨晚
And the colonel's statement did
也的确派上用场了 对吧
come in useful last night, didn't it?
这样你就有充分的动机证据去
As you now had evidence of a motive,
陷害豪伊斯先生谋杀罪名了
enough to frame Mr Hawes for the murder.
噢 真不走运
Oh, bad luck.
"冷静 罗尼 我来帮你调药"
"Calm down, Ronnie. I'll mix your medicine"
之后你打开煤气就离开了
and turn on the gas as you drift away
还把上校的信留在他身边
and leave the colonel's note by the body.
这可是谋杀啊 安妮
But murder, Anne?
就是为了一个提醒你过去的陌生人吗
For a stranger who reminded you of what might have been?
他不是陌生人
He wasn't a stranger.
但我也没说错
But I was right when I said
我说过一切从此都改变了
that nothing was ever the same again
劳伦斯就是那个没能从战场上回来的人
It was Lawrence who didn't come back from the fighting...
但他最后还是回来了
except that he did
在他被公告战亡的四年之后
four years after he'd been reported dead,
而那时候 我已经是普罗瑟罗太太了
and by then, I was Mrs Protheroe.
是他找的你吗
He found you?
当他得知我结婚后 就打消了这个念头
He was too decent to try when he heard I'd married.
是我找的他
I found him.
一篇杂志文章写的关于
A magazine article
一位死里逃生的新晋年轻艺术家
about the rising young artist back from the dead.
我们做错了什么
What did we do wrong?
你居然问我这个?
You ask me that?
我们哪里露出了破绽?
What mistake did we make?
当你和他从木屋里出来
When you came out of the shed with him
你还是和以往一样
you were the same woman.
你没有对你所爱的人道句永别
You hadn't said goodbye forever to the man you loved.
这你都能看得出来吗
You could tell that?
你以为我没试过
You think I've never...
我也在战争中失去了所爱
I lost someone in the war...
他因战亡得到了勋章
..who got a medal for dying.
由他的妻子好好珍藏着
His wife will have cherished it.
他的妻子?
His wife?
那这对你就轻松多了 简
Easier for you, then, Jane.
他死了
He was dead.
你就不用在对错之间做选择
You didn't have to choose between right and wrong.
亲爱的 当你志愿当兵时
When you volunteered, darling
你选择了去尽你的义务
you made a choice to do your duty.
- 是的 - 我也要做出我的选择了
- Yes. - I've had to make a choice too.
而我也选择去尽我的义务
I've chosen to do my duty.
平安回来 但是为了你的妻子 不是为了我
Come back safe, but for your wife, not for me.
简
Jane...
别这样 如果我不是为了你回来 那就
Please, if I can't come back for you, then there's...
简!
Jane!
劳伦斯!劳伦斯!
Lawrence! Lawrence!
你吃炖鱼配上杏子酸辣酱时 我就怀疑了
It's the apricot chutney with fish stew that gave me inkling
你什么时候发现的
When did you find out?
我表哥今早打电话过来确认的
My cousin called this morning to confirm it.
难怪了
Of course!
他就是梅尔切斯特的那个医生 对吧
He's that doctor in Melchester, isn't he?
那个很英俊的年轻人
Rather a handsome young man.
我不想去海多克医生那里看
I didn't want to see Dr Haydock.
哎 你也知道村里的八卦啦
Well, you know village gossip.
我也想先确认了再说
And I wanted to be sure first.
她跟我说她是去的伦敦
She told me she'd gone to London.
我从没怀疑过一丁点
I never suspected a thing.
我们在天上的父
Our Father who art in heaven,
愿人都尊你的名为圣
hallowed be thy name.
愿你的国降临
Thy kingdom come.
愿您的旨意行在地上 如同行在天上
Thy will be done on earth as it is in heaven.
我们日用的饮食 今日赐给我们 免我们的债
Give us this day our daily bread. Forgive us our trespasses.
如同我们免了人的债
As we forgive those who trespass against us.
不叫我们遇见试探
And lead us not into temptation.
救我们脱离凶恶
But deliver us from evil.